So let's consider
a first concrete Petri
net, in
its graphical representation.
We will get to
know a mathematical representation later.
But we'll introduce this informally
first about the graphical representation.
And in particular, this video will be
about introducing the notion of firing as well.
So what do
we have here?
A Petri net
represented with these two
types of ultimately nodes
and their connections between them.
I had already
briefly mentioned on a
previous slide that these
circles are called places.
And they're thought of as
sort of storage places for resources.
Where resources could be quite different things
depending on the system that's being modeled.
So simply the input
data for a process
or actually material resources like
the snacks in a snack machine.
Or simply logical
preconditions for individual actions.
Input signals/things that might
somehow be relevant as
preconditions for actions in the
system or processes in the system.
So these are these circles that
are initially thought to be empty.
And then in these circles, on
these storage places, so-called tokens can lie.
These are
also called tokens.
These small filled circles, which could
lie on the previously still empty
larger circles, these
would be the resources.
So the places
are places for resources,
and then these small
filled circles are concrete resources.
And there could be several of
them on one place, or none.
Now here is one token
on each of these two places.
There are no tokens
on the other three places.
This can
also be different.
There could be
several tokens lying here.
Or there could be tokens everywhere, or there
could be no tokens anywhere, as in this case.
That makes then in
each case a system condition.
So whether there are no tokens at all
on these five places or one token each,
or two tokens up here
and three tokens down here,
that makes up a
system state in its entirety.
If we think back
to the flat state
diagrams, then we had the individual
states, which were then connected with arrows.
And basically one state in such
a flat state diagram would correspond to
an overall
configuration, one way
in which the locations of such a Petri
net may or may not be assigned to tokens.
And then there's this other kind
of nodes in this Petri net graph.
These are
the rectangles here.
Sometimes I'll draw
them as squares.
Anyway, with corners
and not as circles.
And these are
the so-called (system) transitions.
So the idea then is that by the
arrows going in or out to these rectangles,
it shows under what circumstances one
overall state can transition to another.
We will discuss this in a
moment, what for example to this transition
the incoming/outgoing
arrows mean concretely.
And that will be that they somehow cause
the tokens to be located somewhere else afterwards.
So the structure of
the Petri net remains
the same, the places/transitions remain the same,
but the tokens can be in other places.
Then we have a new overall state
of the Petri net as a whole.
And the transitions describe, record how
to get from one state to another.
And that is, so to speak,
recorded locally at a position in
a controlled way
for each transition.
This is again different from flat
state diagrams, where you can't necessarily
read/recognize the preconditions for individual
actions concentrated at one position.
Okay, so this
notion of transition and
in/out arrows is
obviously very central.
So let's shed some
more light on this.
A transition in general
is just such a rectangle.
That can be connected to several
of the places/circles, by incoming/outgoing arrows.
And it can
be quite different.
There could be no incoming arrows at
all, or more than two, or only one.
So it
is completely free.
It depends on the concrete Petri
net we are dealing with and
the places that lie
before the corresponding transition.
So they are not graphically in front of it, but
they are in front of it with respect to the arrows.
They do not necessarily have to
be shown above as in the example.
They could also
lie somewhere else.
But the point is, those places that
have an incoming arrow into a transition are
called preconditions
of that transition.
So those are places where tokens should be
located that will be consumed by the transition.
There on the left
are these incoming arrows.
And all places that are
located after a specific transition
are called postconditions
of this transition.
So these are places into
which tokens can be generated.
And the transitions are
the actual information carriers.
There it is
recorded:
How do
the tokens change?
So the transitions together with their
pre- and post-conditions are the central
information carriers in the
representation of a Petri net.
So it could be
for example like this:
Here are two tokens on these two
places and then this transition could fire.
And that would cause those two tokens
to be consumed and new tokens to
be created on
the three postcondition sites.
So that's not like a token
could move through here or that
could happen independently
for the two inputs.
But rather both inputs are consumed at the
same time and a token is deposited on
all three outputs, in this specific case
of a transition designed in this way.
Of course, if the constellation
is different, then it is analog.
And exactly this change, the removal of
the tokens of the precondition and then
simultaneous generation of the tokens in the
postcondition, is called firing of this one transition.
And of course, if there
are many transitions in the Petri
net, then this can
happen at different places.
And it depends in each
case on the pre- and post-conditions
what exactly this does
to a system state.
This can be more general
than here in the example.
Here, by chance, it looked like
that, for example, there was exactly
one token here and afterwards
exactly one token in the postconditions.
There could also have been
more than one token here before.
So here could have been
two tokens and one token.
Then one of these two would be
removed and the one that was here.
In general, there can
be more than one token.
It is also possible to consume
more than one token per arrow.
Then you have to
note that on the arrow.
We will
discuss how
this is displayed exactly and what
effects this has on the firing.
It could also be that there are no incoming
arrows at all or no outgoing arrows at all.
This is then called either
sources or sinks, such transitions.
We will get to
know that concretely, too.
And unlike in this very simple example,
it doesn't have to be the case
that there are empty
places for the post-condition places.
Tokens could have
already been placed here.
Then some more would be
added by firing this transition.
So very general
constellations are conceivable.
Neither must everything have
been empty here before,
nor must everything be
empty up here after firing.
So if for example two tokens
would have been here, and the transition
demands just one token from this place, then
afterwards just one token would have been here.
So all this
is possible.
We can go through this again
with the example from the slide before,
for some
concrete situations.
For example, let's take this initial
situation as it was on the slide.
Then we
can ask ourselves:
Where could we
fire here at all?
Which of the four
transitions could be fired?
And well, it must always be the
case that the tokens are actually present
in the places from
which tokens are requested.
So for example this transition here
on the left could not be fired
in the
current system state.
Why?
Because it would request
a token from this place.
But there are
no tokens there.
This space
is empty.
Then this
transition can't fire.
And the same would be
true for this and this transition.
On the other hand, this
transition here could actually fire.
Why?
Because for all incoming arrows of
this transition there is actually a token.
So this
transition would fire.
And that would mean that the token would disappear
and a token would be added here and here.
Okay, that was also the only
possible step in the case just now.
So and then
it could go on.
Now we have a
new constellation of the Petri
net, i.e. a new assignment
of the places with tokens.
And then we
could ask ourselves again:
What is
possible now?
So obviously this transition
can't directly fire again now.
Because it has now
no more tokens in its
precondition, which
would allow firing.
But for example this
transition could fire now.
Because it now has a
token on the only precondition place.
So this transition could fire
now, it is active now.
It's ready
to fire now.
Okay, and if we just do
that, now this token would disappear because
it's consumed by the transition, and
a token would be created here.
That is, the next
state would be this.
And then you can
think about other processes.
What could
happen now?
For example, now this transition could
fire because it is justified by this.
We could also
have imagined that
this transition would fire at first
and maybe the other one later.
But we just happened to decide that
we would do it in that order.
But there is a
certain non-determinism, that is,
the order is not necessarily fixed
and determined as only one possible sequence.
That's
called non-determinism.
In the case here, I have
now reached the initial position again.
Now, if I want to continue, I
would have to fire this transition again.
Because we had already discussed that
nothing else works in this situation.
So I fire this again and
maybe I decide now next time not
to necessarily have
the same sequence again.
So to fire that
and to fire that.
Maybe now I
decide to fire here.
I may do that because I can
always execute one of the possible activated transitions.
And this transition is
also activated because it has
exactly one precondition place and
there is a token there.
So we could then consume the
token from here, redeposit it here.
Well, what else would
be possible after that?
Now only this
transition would be fireable.
This is the only transition
that actually still finds enough tokens
on its precondition places,
in this case one.
So we could fire like this
and then it doesn't go any further.
We can't do another step here, because
none of the transitions here are enabled.
That means, in that case, we would
now have maneuvered ourselves into a dead end.
I had already said that, that
is a general term for Petri nets:
The Deadlock.
Now we would
have reached a deadlock.
Because at a point before that,
we decided non-deterministically to execute this
transition, which ultimately takes a resource
out of the system, so to speak.
From down here, that
token never gets anywhere else.
And the only
possible progress left would
be to execute this
transition again at some point.
But it won't come to fruition if
it can never find a token here.
Then we would have reached
a deadlock in that case now.
The system
is not deadlock-free.
And that was basically because we
made an unfavorable choice at that
point to
execute that transition.
It's not like that
was the only possible choice.
If we look closely here,
particularly with respect to this point,
there is a possible
conflict in the Petri net.
Because here this lower transition would have been
activated as well as this above one, but of
course not both
at the same time.
So they can't
both get their way.
Because this transition wants a token from
here, this transition wants a token from here.
So these two transitions are in
conflict with respect to this resource.
And, if we unfortunately decided
in the example to give
preference to the lower transition, that
is, to pass on the token,
then we have ultimately maneuvered
the system into a dead end.
And these are precisely questions that
can then be investigated for Petri nets.
Are there
conflicts like that?
Is there this kind of
non-determinism where we have to decide?
When do we have these kinds of
conflicts? What are the consequences of that?
Can we get
into situations, say,
where the system is then dead
because no further steps are possible?
Or can we perhaps always avoid
this happening for a concrete system?
These are general questions that
we can answer for Petri nets.
Here it was only a matter
of introducing firing as a concept.